A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Program Staff Files FA576
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Program Staff Files
1955-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA576
4.8 Cubic Feet 12 letter document boxes, 1 half-legal box.
The National Affairs Program Files span in date from 1955 to 1978 and comprise of the office files of David B. Carlson, Jr., John R. Coleman, Christopher F. Edley, Ronald T. Gault, Sanford M. Jaffe, Eamon Kelly and William Pincus. Highlights of the collection include Government and Law files on the Foundation's support for legal aid clinics, civil rights litigation and minority representation in the legal field. Each individual's files have been organized into its own series. David B. Carlson's files date from 1968-1971 and consist of subject files primarily concerning Urban and Metropolitan Development grantees and grant evaluations. John R. Coleman's files date from 1966-1967 and consist of grant reviews. Christopher F. Edley's files date from 1959-1972 and consist of chron correspondence and subject files relating to the Foundation's Government and Law grant making and work in the field of corrections. Ronald T. Gault's files date from 1969-1976 and consist mainly of correspondence and memoranda regarding Travel and Study Awards. Sanford M. Jaffe's files date from 1974-1978 and consist mainly of memoranda, meeting minutes, and proposals from the Foundation's Committee on Human Rights and Social Process. Eamon Kelly's files date from 1966-1970 and consist of chron correspondence, Board of Directors meeting minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and background information on the North Carolina Fund. William Pincus's files date from 1955-1967 and consist of memoranda on budget and grant evaluations and his writings on topics such as legal education.
(12 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Custodial History note
This collection appears to have been combined from the office files of seven National Affairs program officers, although the provenance is unclear in that regard. Several boxes in the collection were misattributed to National Affairs. These include: •Three cubic feet of office files of William O. Sweeney, International Division (these were processed separately). •One cubic foot box was identified as originating from the Population program and was held for processing as part of that collection. •One box was identified as a PRI file misattributed to National Affairs, and was transferred to the Closed Grant Office for separate offsite storage. •Three boxes of files were identified as belonging to Robert B. Goldmann, and were held for later processing with additional National Affairs files originating from Mr. Goldmann. •One box was identified as investment files from the Office of the Treasurer and was held for separate processing as part of the office files of Roger G. Kennedy.
Biographical/Historical note
David B. Carlson, Jr. served as a Program Advisor for the Urban and Metropolitan Development program between 1969 and 1971. He later worked for the Foundation as a consultant specializing in Community Development Corporations (1988).
John R. Coleman was a labor economist who earned a B.A at the University of Toronto and an M.A. and Ph.D from the University of Chicago. He joined the Foundation as Associate Director of Economic Development and Administration and, in 1966, became Program Officer in Charge of Social Development. He left the Foundation in 1967 to become President of Haverford College.
Christopher F. Edley was born on January 1, 1928. He received a B.A. in Political Science (1949) and a LL.B from Harvard Law School (1953). He joined the Foundation in 1963 as a Program Officer in Social Development with shared responsibility for the administration of justice program and a program to assist minority groups. He was the first African American Program Officer hired by the Ford Foundation. Mr. Edley moved to the Government and Law program in 1966 and in December of 1967 he was appointed Program Officer in Charge of the program. He left the Foundation in 1973 to become President of the United Negro College Fund. He died on May 5, 2003, at the age of 75.
Ronald T. Gault was a Program Officer in Social Development from 1969 to 1978, when left the Foundation to serve as an advisor to New York City Mayor Edward Koch. Shortly thereafter Mayor Koch appointed him Commissioner of Employment.
Sanford M. Jaffe earned a B.A. from Rutgers University and an LL.B. from Harvard Law School. Mr. Jaffe was the Program Officer in Charge of Government and Law from 1968 to 1983. He departed the Foundation in 1983 to become Director of the Dispute Resolution Center at New York University's School of Law. Eamon Kelly was born in New York City. He earned a B.A. from Fordham University and from 1960 to 1965 earned an M.A. and Ph.D in economics from Columbia University. Dr. Kelly joined the Ford Foundation in 1969 and served as Officer in Charge for the Office of Social Development. In 1977, he was appointed Program Officer in Charge for Program Related Investments. He left the Foundation in 1981 to become the 13th President of Tulane University.
William Pincus joined the Foundation as a Program Associate for the Public Affairs Division around 1955, and from 1965 to 1968 served as a Program Officer for Government and Law. Beginning in 1955 Mr. Pincus helped lay the groundwork for the Foundation's support for legal aid clinics at law schools. In 1969, Mr. Pincus became the first President of the Council on Legal Education for Professional Responsibility (CLEPR), a non-profit organization established by the Ford Foundation to support legal aid clinics.
Biographical/Historical note
The Foundation's work in urban poverty began with the establishment of the Public Affairs Program in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to strive toward greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, a National Affairs Division was created to focus on some of the deep-rooted problems facing American society. The program areas under this new National Affairs Division included Social Development, and Urban and Metropolitan Development. The United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) replaced the National Affairs Division in 1981 after a Foundation-wide reorganization.
Related Archival Materials note
FA627 Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Government and Law Program, Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe – This collection consists of chronological files, correspondence, inter-office memoranda and minutes documenting his activities from 1970 to 1981 in the positions of Program Officer and Program Officer in Charge.
Ford Foundation Resource Identifier: ACC95/3 – Records, 1953-1976, 1967-1976 (bulk). This collection of National Affairs Division office files consists of files maintained by the following staff members: Christopher Edley, Sanford M. Jaffe, William Pincus, Esther Schachter, Robert Goldmann, George Esser, Mitchell Sviridoff, David B. Carlson, John R. Coleman, Thomas E. Cooney, Ronald T. Gault, Eamon Kelly, Robert Schrank, William Pendleton and Louis Winnick. Also included are the chronological correspondence files of the Government and Law and the Resources and Environment programs. There is some material, spanning from 1953 to 1967, created by National Affairs' predecessor program, Public Affairs. (This collection has not yet been received by the Rockefeller Archive Center)
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into seven series.
Scope and Contents note
The National Affairs Program Files span from 1955 to 1978. The collection is comprised of the combined office files of David B. Carlson, Jr., John R. Coleman, Christopher F. Edley, Ronald T. Gault, Sanford M. Jaffe, Eamon Kelly and William Pincus. Each individual's files have been arranged as a separate series.
The files are particularly illustrative of the Foundation's Government and Law Program from the 1950s to the 1970s. William Pincus, one of the earliest Foundation program officers in the area of government and law, helped establish the Foundation's role in supporting and funding legal aid clinics, which were intended to help the impoverished. This support for legal aid and legal education then led the Foundation over time to support civil rights litigation and attempts to improve minority representation in the legal field. For example the Foundation evaluated of a proposal to establish a National Indian Rights Association (1969) to potentially improve the status of Native Americans in American society.
Other Foundation efforts toward improving the presence of minorities in education were made through grant Travel and Study Awards. Many awards to minority scholars were intended to support research such as a study of African Business (1972-1973) or a book on the student civil rights movement of the 1960s (1974). In addition, Dr. Eamon Kelly's files shed light on the Foundation's support for the North Carolina Fund, which was a series of state-sponsored experimental poverty relief programs in the late 60s.
This collection also shows the interrelation between program areas within the same division, particularly in the files of Christopher Edley who transferred from Social Development to Government and Law. As part of the Social Development unit Mr. Edley oversaw grants for civil rights housing litigation, and after transferring oversaw grants to increase the number of minority lawyers. These were slightly differing approaches to the goals of relieving poverty and improving of minority civil rights.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- David B. Carlson, Jr., 1968-1971; I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series holds Mr. Carlson's subject files. The files primarily concern grantees and include grantee evaluations. Also available are program recommendations for grant actions for Urban and Metropolitan Development.
  - Action for Washington Park and Community Development (Rockford, IL) -- Correspondence, Proposal Evaluation, Proposal for Outer City Project, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Log of Incoming Memoranda and Correspondence Listing Subjects and File Locations, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Community Design Centers -- Correspondence, Background, Proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Proposal and Grantee Evaluations -- A-H (1 of 2), 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Proposal and Grantee Evaluations -- I-Z (2 of 2), 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Press Releases Re: Minority Business and Community Enterprises, Low- and Moderate-Income Housing for Minority Groups, etc., 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Staff Instructional Memoranda Re: Responding to Incoming Proposals, Disposition of Reports from Travel and Study Awardees, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foundation for Cooperative Housing -- Correspondence Re: Grant, Grant Action, Background on Grantee, May 1970-Jan 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Housing Development Corporations -- Draft Questions for Ford Foundation Analysis of Performance, Notes, Mar 16, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Illinois Housing Development Corporation -- Correspondence Re: Adjustment to Comply with Tax Reform Act of 1969, Mar-Jun 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mexican American Housing Proposals and Correspondence -- League of United Latin American Citizens, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Monitoring Reports for Philadelphia Council for Community Advancement and St. Louis Housing Fund, Aug 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mortgage Opportunities Corporation -- Robert A. Thompson Correspondence Commending Ford Foundation Support for Mortgage Banks for Black Southerners, Nov 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Affairs Program Related Investment Action Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Service to Regional Councils -- Grant Action, Board Meeting Memoranda and Agendas, Mar 1970-Jan 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Urban Coalition -- Correspondence Re: Grant, Updates, Merger and Name Change, Background on Grantee, Jul 1969-Dec 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philadelphia Council for Community Advancement -- Monitoring Report, Grantee Progress Report, Notes, Aug 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rural Housing Alliance (RHA) -- Memoranda Re: RHA Tax Status, Statement to House Banking and Currency Committee on Pending Legislation, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Southwest Council of La Raza -- Proposal for Educational Reform for Mexican American Students, Grantee Executive Report, Clippings, Dec 1969-Apr 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - St. Louis Housing Fund -- Monitoring Report, Aug 16, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Urban and Metropolitan Development (UMD) Program Recommendations for Grant Action (1 of 3), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Urban and Metropolitan Development (UMD) Program Recommendations for Grant Action (2 of 3), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Urban and Metropolitan Development (UMD) Program Recommendations for Grant Action (3 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Urban and Metropolitan Development (UMD) Program Recommendations for Grant Action by Robert W. Chandler, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Watts Labor Community Action Committee -- Correspondence Re: Grant Terms, Recommendation for Grant Action, Feb-May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- John R. Coleman, 1966-1967; II
  Dr. Coleman's files consist of grant reviews including the North Carolina Fund (1967) and the Oakland Economic Development Council (1966).
  - Reviews -- Action for Boston Community Development, Jun 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reviews -- Community Progress, Inc. of New Haven, CT, Aug 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reviews -- North Carolina Fund, Jan-Feb 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reviews -- Oakland Economic Development Council, Jul 29, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reviews -- United Planning Organization, May 18, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Christopher Edley, Bulk, 1964-1971 1959-1973; 1964-1971; III
  Mr. Edley's files comprise the largest series in this collection. A limited amount of chronological correspondence is available for the period from July 1968 to March 1969. The largest group of records, Mr. Edley's subject files, have been arranged in alphabetical order. Mr. Edley's files reflect his position in charge of Government and Law grant-making, including documents related to the Foundation's work in the area of Corrections. The documents, which date between 1964 and 1973, include memoranda on prison education programs, correspondence about and results from a Foundation-funded survey of state correctional research capabilities, discussion papers, and background information.
  - Boston Legal Aid -- Comments on Proposal for Community Legal Clinic, Notes, Draft Proposal, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Budget FY 1965-1967 -- Memoranda Re: Funding for Law and Justice in Budget, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Correspondence File (1 of 3), Jul-Sep 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Correspondence File (2 of 3), Oct-Dec 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Correspondence File (3 of 3), Jan-Mar 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Civil Rights: The Negro Movement for Equal Opportunity" -- Discussion Paper Drafts, Comments, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Corrections -- Correspondence Re: Ford Foundation Correctional Survey, Crime Advisory Committee Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Corrections -- Ford Foundation Survey of State Correctional Research Capacities, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Corrections -- Memoranda Re: Prison Litigation, Discussion Paper, Background, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Court Administration -- Correspondence Re: New York State Court Reform, National Conference on the Judiciary, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Court Design -- Correspondence Re: Architecture, Background, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Criminal Justice Centers -- Proposal, Ford Foundation Memoranda Re: College Probation Programs, Reports, Background, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Delta Opportunities Corporation Self-Help Housing Project -- Proposal, Site Visits, Grant Review Memoranda, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Drugs -- Proposal for National Committee on Narcotics, Background (1 of 2), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Drugs -- FAP Re: Drug Abuse Problem, Ford Foundation Reports on Drugs (2 of 2), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Electoral Reform -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Potential Ford Foundation Support for Registering Young Voters, Background Letters to Editor Re: Electoral College Abolition, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation-Sponsored Community Development Conference, San Juan, Puerto Rico -- Agenda, Papers, Participants List, Press Release, Dec 13-16, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Study Group on Manpower Planning and Development -- Memoranda, Agenda, Meeting Minutes, Feb 23, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Glueck, Sheldon -- Correspondence Re: Harvard Criminology Study, 1959-1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Housing -- Outline for Report on Civil Rights Housing Litigation, Apr 2-Jun 1, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Howard University Law School Testing and Pilot Remedial Program in Reading and Writing -- Interim Report, Background, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Howard University Law School Workshop Conference on Rule of Law and Federal Grant Making Agencies -- Legal Questions for Consideration, Clippings Re: Child Development Group of Mississippi (CDGM), Nov 13-14, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Indians -- Background Report on American Indian Civil Rights (1 of 2), May 26, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Indians -- Proposal, Proposal Evaluations for National Indian Rights Association (2 of 2), 1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Manhattan Bail Project, Vera Foundation -- Reports, Clippings on Experience of Poor with Criminal Justice and Vera's Work, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mexican Americans -- Mexican-American Study Project Report, Ford Foundation Public Affairs Staff Meeting Summary on Mexican Americans, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mississippi Delta Ministry, National Council of the Churches of Christ -- Report of Evaluation Committee, Background on Delta Ministry, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Mississippi Summer Project -- Correspondence, Journal Entries of Peter Marcuse, Jun-Oct 1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - (2nd) National Conference on Research and Teaching in Criminology, University of Cambridge -- Program, Participant List, Course Schedule, Jun 29-Jul 1, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - National Conference on Social Welfare, Atlantic City, NJ -- Summary of Conference and Sessions Attended, Conference Book, May 23-28, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Negro (General) -- Reports, Reprinted Monographs (1 of 2), 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Negro (General) -- Reports, Reprinted Monographs (2 of 2), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Negro Lawyers in the United States, 1966: An Economic Study" (consultant report), Oct 1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Society of Newspaper Editors Seminar on Crime, Law Enforcement and the Courts, Harrisburg, PA -- Speakers' Profiles, Papers, Background on Pennsylvania Corrections, Apr 1-3, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Social Mobility of the American Negro: Prospects for a Program of Studies" (discussion paper by Otis Dudley Duncan), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Trip to London/Europe -- Correspondence, Notes on Meetings with Various Criminal Justice Officials, etc., Jul 17-Aug 18, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - (3rd) United Nations Congress on the Prevention of Crime and the Treatment of Offenders -- Abstracts of Working Papers, Information Notes, Aug 9-18, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Ronald T. Gault, 1969-1976; IV
  Mr. Gault's files primarily reflect his supervision of the Travel and Study Awards program and contain correspondence with and memoranda about award recipients and potential award candidates. There are also several files for the Union Leadership Training Program at the University of California (1970-1972).
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Brown, Alma A. --Correspondence, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Davis, King E. -- Review of Black United Fund (1 of 2), 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Davis, King E. -- Review of Black United Fund (2 of 2), 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Evans, Ronald -- Correspondence, Notes, 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- General -- Memoranda, Notes, Award Lists, 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Harris, Marion -- Correspondence, Memoranda, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Johnson, Willard -- Study of African Business, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- MBA Students, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Noble, Jeanne -- Correspondence, Memoranda re: Evaluation of National Council of Negro Women, etc., 1965-1971 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - United Black Appeal -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Use of Legal Action, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - University of California Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Labor Studies, Union Leadership Training Program, etc., 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - University of California Evaluations of Minority Union Leadership Training Program, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - University of California Grant Monitoring Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Urban Institute -- Notes and Memoranda Re: CDC Review, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Sanford M. Jaffe, 1974-1978; V
  The files of Mr. Jaffe largely consist of the memoranda, meeting minutes, and proposals for the Foundation's Committee on Human Rights and Social Process. A few of files also contain recommendations for the Government and Law Program.
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Human Rights and Social Process -- Memoranda, Meeting Minutes, Proposals (1 of 4), Jan-Jun, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Human Rights and Social Process -- Memoranda, Meeting Minutes, Proposals (2 of 4), Aug-Oct, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Human Rights and Social Process -- Memoranda, Meeting Minutes, Proposals (3 of 4), Nov-Dec 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Human Rights and Social Process -- Memoranda, Meeting Minutes, Proposals (4 of 4), Jan 1977-Mar 1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation Conference on Human Rights and Intellectual Freedom, Jan 19, 1976 -- Memoranda, Paper, Nov 1975-Jan 1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ford Foundation International Division Conference on Human Rights, Sep 20, 1975 -- Memoranda Re: Comments on Papers, Papers, Notes (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Government and Law Program Recommendations for Grant/DAP Action (1 of 3), Jun 1976-Feb 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Government and Law Program Recommendations for Grant/DAP Action (2 of 3), Mar-May 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Government and Law Program Recommendations for Grant/DAP Action (3 of 3), Jun-Oct 1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)